Speaker: Five couples left London at the start of the race,
and one was eliminated during the journey, leaving four to cross the finish line in Singapore.
The couples had travelled by train, bus, boat, and taxi, through mountains, deserts, and tropical islands.
They had worked in farms, flower shops, hostels,
and animal sanctuaries on their journeys, exploring different cultures, taking risks,
and confronting their fears.
The eventual winners were 61-year-old retired teachers Tony and Elaine,
who claimed the £20,000 prize money.
Natalie and Shameema finished third overall and Josh and Felix last
– they didn’t have enough money to reach the final checkpoint,
but were given the money by Natalie and Shameema so that they could complete the race.
The contestants remember relying on people’s help, laughing,
connecting without a common language, feeling exhausted, despondent, and jubilant,
finding their courage, and discovering that if you show respect, kindness is universal.
The ‘loveliest moments’, they all say, were chatting with people on trains
– tales of hair-plaiting, exchanging chocolate for chicken, sharing photos,
the gesture of a hand on heart.
The teams returned home in December.
Before jumping back into work, Josh and Felix took a holiday with their girlfriends.
Natalie went on a month’s silent meditation.
Shameema enrolled in a boxing class and won a match in front of 1,000 people (including her daughters and Natalie).
Josh recalls that at first the production crew tried to ‘gee up’ the competitive side of the race,
but soon, he says, ‘They realized it was about the human stories. It’s always about the human stories.’